<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-16T09:47:56+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Cambridge Refugee Resettlement Campaign</title><subtitle>Cambridge Refugee Resettlement Campaign helps those who have arrived in Cambridge seeking safety, in all ways from the practical provision of clothes and furniture, to helping with language learning and social differences.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">UK Borders Bill campaign</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/07/14/borders-bill.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UK Borders Bill campaign" /><published>2021-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/07/14/borders-bill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/07/14/borders-bill.html">&lt;p&gt;The UK Government’s Nationality and Borders Bill is due for its second reading next week, and is essentially the same as the &lt;a href=&quot;/npfi-2021.html&quot;&gt;New Plan for Immigration&lt;/a&gt;. It is being rushed through before the results of the consultation are known, and before all the obvious flaws that were pointed out by expert groups have been made public or indeed addressed. The advice we gave about the NPfI still stands: it is illegal and immoral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some resources specifically about this Bill that you might like to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Joint Council for the Welfare of Immigrants &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jcwi.org.uk/nationality-and-borders-bill-second-reading-briefing&quot;&gt;briefing&lt;/a&gt; on the second reading of the Nationality and Borders Bill.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Refugee Council’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.refugeecouncil.org.uk/information/resources/nationality-and-borders-bill-second-reading-refugee-council-briefing/&quot;&gt;briefing&lt;/a&gt; on the second reading of the Nationality and Borders Bill.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biduk.org/articles/850-bid-s-response-to-the-nationality-and-borders-bill&quot;&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; to the Nationality and Borders Bill from Bail for Immigration Detainees.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liberty’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libertyhumanrights.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/Libertys-second-reading-briefing-on-the-Nationality-and-Borders-Bill.pdf&quot;&gt;briefing&lt;/a&gt; (PDF) on the second reading of the Nationality and Borders Bill.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Safe Passage’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1iqlPEHKz-WEy2sAf9y50RwVTCYZ4JQ8X/view&quot;&gt;briefing&lt;/a&gt; on the second reading of the Nationality and Borders Bill.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Together With Refugees &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1AODOjRwFQkIyLc7YaqUZAuKxEgvu-GVi/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;webinar recording&lt;/a&gt; about the Bill (MP4 file on Google Drive).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One Strong Voice’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.onestrongvoice.org.uk/petition.html&quot;&gt;petition&lt;/a&gt; putting forward more humane ideas for our asylum system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please write to your MP pointing out the problems with the Bill and asking for them to oppose it. Use their email address if you have it, or you can use this WriteToThem form to find their details and send a message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- WriteToThem conventional box, start --&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;padding:0; border:1px solid #101820; width:14em; margin: 0;
           background-color:#FFAB70;&quot;&gt;
   &lt;form method=&quot;get&quot; action=&quot;https://www.writetothem.com/&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
       &lt;div style=&quot;background-color:#FFAB70;padding:3px; color:#101820;&quot;&gt;
               &lt;strong&gt;Contact Your MP&lt;/strong&gt;
       &lt;/div&gt;
       &lt;div style=&quot;margin:0.5em; color:#101820; background-color: #FFAB70;&quot;&gt;
           &lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom:0.25em;&quot;&gt;Enter your Postcode below:&lt;/div&gt;
           &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; name=&quot;pc&quot; size=&quot;13&quot; /&gt;
           &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;a&quot; value=&quot;westminstermp&quot; /&gt;
           &lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; value=&quot;Go&quot; /&gt;
       &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/form&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- WriteToThem conventional box, end--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an example below that you can use as a template, but please customise your own letter rather than just copying and pasting. Otherwise, your MP will receive lots of identical letters that they’re likely to ignore!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am writing to you as my MP ahead of the second reading of the new Borders and Immigration Bill on 19 July. It is a shame that the results of the public consultation on the Government’s &lt;em&gt;New Plan for Immigration&lt;/em&gt; have not been made public, because these should inform the Parliamentary discussion of the new Bill. I understand that many legal and social-reform experts and organisations have made important points about the Government’s proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, Cambridgeshire is an area with a large but invisible immigrant community, who are often white, educated and economically very productive. But Cambridge also has a long history of welcoming people seeking refuge, from Belgians displaced by the First World War, Jewish academics and Basque children fleeing the rise of fascism in Europe, to Vietnamese Boat People and dissidents from the former Eastern bloc, South Africa and Chile. This is something many of us are very proud of. Cambridge would simply not be the economic, intellectual and scientific powerhouse that it is without immigrants, some of whom arrived seeking asylum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambridgeshire is not anti-refugee, so I hope you will reflect that with your vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Home Secretary has said that the Government’s aim with this Bill is to make the system simpler, fairer and quicker. Few would disagree with this aim - recent polls suggest 60% of British people support reform along these principles, although I have no doubt it is higher locally. However, the actual proposals in the Bill introduce a system that is unfair to the asylum seekers in need of help, and would be simpler and quicker only for the Home Office because the Bill removes people’s rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows that the asylum system needs reform, but it is clear that the bottleneck is with the Home Office and its decision-making: the backlog waiting for initial decisions has risen even though asylum claims have been falling over recent years. Surely this would be the place to begin reform, rather than trampling on our honourable traditions of sanctuary by instituting a two-tier system whereby how someone arrives to seek asylum is more important than why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Bill will not ‘streamline’ or ‘improve’ the current system because much of it, according to a UN statement, contravenes international law or is impracticable or unethical. These are just a few of the many concerns raised by those who work in the sector but who were not consulted in the formulation of this Bill. Denying the opportunity to appeal poor decisions and penalising traumatised people if they are viewed as uncooperative make miscarriages of justice more likely and will make lengthy and costly legal proceedings inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask you, therefore, to speak for the solid majority of the British people who support reform but stand by the principle that those who need protection should get it. This should apply to anyone who arrives in the UK, by whatever means, who has a well-founded fear of persecution or harm in their home country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yours sincerely,&lt;br /&gt;
[Your Name]&lt;br /&gt;
[Also add your address, to show that you are a constituent]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html">The UK Government’s Nationality and Borders Bill is due for its second reading next week, and is essentially the same as the New Plan for Immigration. It is being rushed through before the results of the consultation are known, and before all the obvious flaws that were pointed out by expert groups have been made public or indeed addressed. The advice we gave about the NPfI still stands: it is illegal and immoral.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Socials are back!</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/06/18/socials-are-back.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Socials are back!" /><published>2021-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/06/18/socials-are-back</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/06/18/socials-are-back.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-05-22-maypole.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pub in Cambridge&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are very excited to announce that we will be resuming regular volunteer socials on the fourth Wednesday of each month at the Maypole on Portugal Place. The next one will be next Wednesday 24th June, from 7.30pm. Please let us know by email to &lt;em&gt;admin at cambridgerefugees.org&lt;/em&gt; if you will be coming as numbers will be limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope to re-start Refugee Socials as soon as this is allowed indoors. We would love to hear from you if you would like to join the team planning and organising the socials, which are likely to be popular when they begin again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Arabic Language and Culture Workshop</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/university-arabic-language-and-culture-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arabic Language and Culture Workshop" /><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/university-arabic-language-and-culture-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/university-arabic-language-and-culture-workshop.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-05-26-arabic-culture.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Patterned tile ceiling&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Cambridge Centre of Islamic Studies is offering CRRC volunteers and their friends the opportunity, as part of Refugee Week, to take part in a workshop entitled &lt;em&gt;An Introduction to Arabic Language and Culture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a virtual event on 18 June, starting at 1pm and lasting about an hour. If you would like to attend, please register your interest &lt;a href=&quot;admin@cambridgerefugees.org&quot;&gt;by email&lt;/a&gt; and a zoom link will be sent out in time for the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Refugees in Museums</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/refugees-in-museums.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Refugees in Museums" /><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/refugees-in-museums</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/refugees-in-museums.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-05-26-issam-kourbaj.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Issam Kourbaj&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Fitzwilliam Museum Virtual Talk, organised as part of Refugee Week at 1.30pm on 17 June, centres around the theme of migration and the refugee crisis in the Mediterranean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event follows a special display by contemporary artist Issam Kourbaj, currently on view at the Fitzwilliam Museum until September 6, 2021. The panel talk aims to highlight the response in contemporary Art and Poetry to the crisis, as well as that of Museums. Panellists include the artist Issam Kourbaj and celebrated poet Ruth Padel, as well as a representative of CRRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details available &lt;a href=&quot;https://refugeeweek.org.uk/events/online-talk-refugees-museums/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creative Workshop with Leila Mehulić</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/creative-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creative Workshop with Leila Mehulić" /><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/creative-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/creative-workshop.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-05-26-creative-workshop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hand-crafted bag&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Art historian and curator Leila Mehulić is running an online creative workshop 2:00 to 3:30pm on 17 June. Exploring themes of objects and memories, participants will consider items from the Higgins Bedford museum’s collection as well as objects associated with journeys from their own homelands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Booking required. For more information, please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://refugeeweek.org.uk/events/workshop-curator-art-historian-leila-mehulic/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gil Loescher Book Launch</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/book-launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gil Loescher Book Launch" /><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/book-launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/26/book-launch.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-05-26-book-cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cover image of 'Refugees: A Very Short Introduction' by Gil Loescher&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Gil Loescher’s last work, &lt;em&gt;Refugees: A Very Short Introduction&lt;/em&gt;, will be launched on 27 May. Published by Oxford University Press, Professor Loescher dedicated a chapter of his book to the work of civil society organisations, inspired by conversations with his daughter Maggie, who is a founder member of CRRC. We are honoured to be mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please register to attend &lt;a href=&quot;https://carleton.ca/lerrn/cu-events/gil-loescher-book-launch/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note that the event begins at 3pm UK time but is being hosted in Canada, so times advertised are EST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copies of the book can be ordered &lt;a href=&quot;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/refugees-a-very-short-introduction-9780198811787&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cook along with Faraj!</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/25/cook-along-with-faraj.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cook along with Faraj!" /><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/25/cook-along-with-faraj</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/25/cook-along-with-faraj.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-03-22-faraj-480.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Faraj smiling in his chef's apron&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the very successful ‘Cook along with Faraj’ event, Faraj has agreed to do it again! We’re not the only ones who were impressed by Faraj: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.itv.com/news/anglia/2021-05-05/from-syrian-refugee-to-cambridge-business-owner-in-3-years&quot;&gt;ITV were, too&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faraj is a fantastic cook who’s trained at Ottolenghi and at Honey &amp;amp; Co. He’s also a Syrian refugee who came to Cambridge 5 years ago, and now has his own catering business. He’s been sharing some of his love of cookery in evenings of cooking and chat, creating some of his favourite Syrian dishes and sharing his recipe and techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to join us for this fantastic event, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/cook-along-with-faraj-tickets-154078193023&quot;&gt;book your place on Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt; and get the list of ingredients you’ll need to have ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Walking Together</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/25/walking-together.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Walking Together" /><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/25/walking-together</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/25/walking-together.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-06-15-friends-meeting-house.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jesus Lane Friends Meeting House&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday 15 June at 7.30pm, a special blended virtual and real world meeting on this year’s Refugee Week theme of ‘We cannot walk alone’. Come and hear the journeys of asylum seekers, refugees and Quaker Friends walking alongside one another: Sharing experiences, creating memories, the stories of people’s lives and how they weave together on the journey of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Jesus Lane Meeting House and via Zoom (details to be announced).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bike project update</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/20/bike-project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bike project update" /><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/20/bike-project</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/20/bike-project.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-05-20-AmandaLavriBike.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amanda with Lavri and his new bike&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A side effect of the pandemic is that there are huge global supply problems. New bikes are very difficult to buy at the moment and, as a result, secondhand bikes have dramatically increased in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Amanda, our Bike Project coordinator (on the left in the first picture, with Lavri from Sudan), has managed to source several bikes for the refugee families, including two brand new ones for two of the boys to cycle to school and this lovely blue one for Salma (pictured below). Amanda is also booking tailored training with Outspoken, and has partnered with a London-based charity which refurbishes bikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-05-20-salma-with-bike.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Salma on her blue bike&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Plan for Immigration</title><link href="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/15/npfi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Plan for Immigration" /><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/15/npfi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cambridgerefugees.org//newslist/2021/05/15/npfi.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-05-15-alexa-netty.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alexa Netty, Executive Director of SolidariTee&quot; class=&quot;float-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRRC trustees have been campaigning over the past month to encourage everyone who cares about refugees to take part in this Government’s public consultation on Priti Patel’s New Plan for Immigration. We held a joint webinar on 22 April with CamCRAG and SolidariTee (right: Alexa Netty, Executive Director of SolidariTee, talks participants through the issues) to help people answer the questionnaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes proposed will bring misery and uncertainty to refugees and asylum-seekers, introducing offshore detention centres, a two-tier system to penalise anyone claiming asylum after reaching the UK in an ‘irregular manner’, a suggestion that small boats in the Channel should be ‘redirected’, which can only lead to more loss of life, and so on. The UNHCR has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unhcr.org/uk/news/press/2021/5/6097bce14/unhcr-deeply-concerned-at-discriminatory-two-tier-uk-asylum-plans-urges.html&quot;&gt;issued a legal opinion&lt;/a&gt; on the proposals confirming that many of them will contravene established international law. The consultation ended on 6 May after a very short window in which objections could be raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its obvious flaws, the New Plan will indeed form the basis of the new Borders Bill introduced in the Queen’s Speech on 11 May. Please consider writing to your MP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="newslist" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>